Guide to the Papers of Mordecai Sheftall (1735-1797), undated, 1761-1867, 1873, 1932, 1941 (bulk 1777-1778) *P-12
American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA and New York, NY
- Subgroup III: Works Progress Administration Guide and Index, 1941
  - Series I: Works Progress Administration Guide, 1941
    A cross mark (X) inserted between family and given names indicates the person could not write (from illiteracy or accident) and that he made his mark.
    An asterisk (*) indicates that a biographical sketch of the person appears in the Biographical Index.
    Following the person's name is the most commonly given rank (military, naval, civilian) and following this, the unit, military and/or naval, with which he was associated. Other ranks and units with which his name appears are enclosed in parentheses.
    Military and naval ranks, as well as units, are abbreviated according to Army and Navy usage, with the exceptions that 1GB, 2GB, 3GB, 4GB stand for First, Second, Third, Fourth Georgia Battalions of Continental troops.
    Following the units mentioned, we give the first and last dates of papers upon which the name appears. Since practically all ration returns and ledger entries in this collection were written in 1778, the year is omitted when the date-span falls entirely within 1778, for the sake of brevity.
    The file box letter and manuscript number of the first and last manuscript dates are given in parentheses. The numbers which appear in brackets between these denote the additional manuscripts in which any given name is found.
    Ten additional sources have been consulted for verification of, or additional information on, names of persons in this list. These sources are:
    A - British Acts of Attainder
    C I, CII, CIII - Candler's Revolutionary Records of Georgia, vols. I, II, III
    D - Disqualifying Act
    H - Heitman's Official Register
    K - Knight's Georgia Roster
    O - Officers Not Exchanged
    P - Parolee List
    R - Revolutionary Soldiers' Receipts
    S.C.P. - Sourth Carolina Pension Roll, U.S. War Dept.
    W - Prisoners of War
    Wil - Wilson's Annals of Georgia
    Example to illustrate these rules of interpretation: 34
    *BOWEN, Oliver; Commodore; Feb. 20.-Aug. 31 (D323 [74] D388); 54, 61, 63, 88, 90, [A; D; H, Capt., 1GB; K, Son of Liberty, member Provincial Congress, Capt. of galley, Commodore.]
    Interpretation: Biographical sketch of Oliver Bowen in biographical Index of this book; his name first appears in this collection under date February 20, 1778, library number D323, last appears under date August 31, 1778, library number D388; appears 74 times between these dates [library has card catalogue for each entry]; his name appears in entries 54, 61, 63, 88, 90 of book; his name appears on British Acts of Attainder and on Disqualifying Act; Heitman lists him as Captain, First Georgia Battalion; Knight lists him as Son of Liberty, member Provincial Congress, Captain of Galley, Commodore."
    Places lists camps, forts, counties, islands, rivers, towns, hospitals, plantations, and inns named within the collection papers.Ships lists names barges, boats, brigs, brigantines, corsairs, cutters, flats, gallies, packets, privateers, prices, schooners, shallops and sloops named in the collection.
    Part III: Works Progress Administration Guide, 1941
    Part III Appendix: Transcripts of Related, Contemporaneous Material from Other Sources including
    --Parole List, June 19, 1779
    --List of Officers Not Exchanged, November 15, 1779
    --British Disqualifying Act, July 1, 1780
    --British Act of Attainder, April 9, 1781
    --Amendment of Act of Attainder, May 19, 1781
    --Minutes of Georgia Executive Council, February 15, 1783
    --Minutes of Georgia Executive Council, April 3, 1778
    --Journal of Georgia House of Assembly, July 29, 1782
    --Georgia Troops during the Revolutionary War
    --Resolution Regarding Soldier's Pay, October 7, 1775
    --Order Book of Samuel Elbert
    --Transcription of Letter of General Samuel Elbert to Colonel Screven
    --Letter from Richard Eastmend to Mordecai Sheftall
    --Appointment of Mordecai Sheftall as Deput Comissary General of Issues
    --Report on the State of Georgia, January 1788
    --Mortgage of St. Catherine's Island, March 17, 1770
    --Plan for Landing French Troops in Savannah to Relieve the Siege
    --Miscellaneous Papers, Mordecai Sheftall
    Part IV: Works Progress Administration Guide, 1941
    Part IV: Historical and Biographical Notes including
    --Biographical Index of Prominent Names
    --Gazeteer of Places Mentioned
    --Georgia Militia during the Revolutionary War
    --Georgia Navy and American Privateering
    --Georgia Navy during the Revolutionary War
    --Governors of Georgia to 1819
    --Chronological List of Revolutionary Battles
    The WPA Guide's remaining sections include a Bibliography of Works Consulted, an Index to Part I of names and places within the WPA Guide, and a list of Publications of the Historical Records Survey including New York City and New York State.
    - "The Sheftall Papers in the Collection of the American Jewish Historical Society: Transcriptions, Excerpts and Lists of Revolutionary Soldiers and Others." Prepared by The Historical Records Survey Division of Community Service Programs, Works Projects Administration, New York, 1941 (Received July 15, 1942) (Copy 1 and Microfilmed) (Box 14)
    - "The Sheftall Papers in the Collection of the American Jewish Historical Society: Transcriptions, Excerpts and Lists of Revolutionary Soldiers and Others." Prepared by The Historical Records Survey Division of Community Service Programs, Works Projects Administration, New York, 1941 (Received July 15, 1942) (Copy 2, Not Microfilmed) (Box 15)
    - "The Sheftall Papers in the Collection of the American Jewish Historical Society: Transcriptions, Excerpts and Lists of Revolutionary Soldiers and Others." Prepared by The Historical Records Survey Division of Community Service Programs, Works Projects Administration, New York, 1941 (Received July 15, 1942) (Copy 3, Not Microfilmed) (Box 16)
    - Case "A" Checklist, undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Case "A" Checklist, undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Case "B" Checklist, undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Case "B" Checklist, undated (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Case "B" Typescript Notes, undated (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Case "F" Checklist, January 22, 1941 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Series II: Index Cards, undated
    The final series in this collection is a set of handwritten index cards containing the research used for the People and Places Indexes of the WPA Guide.
    - Index Cards, undated (Box 17)
- Separated Oversized Material, 1778, 1781, 1786, 1807, 1833, 1857-1858, 1873; 9 oversized OS2 folders.
  This Oversized documents series contains eight large documents (one of which is missing) and a reference to one document that has been moved to the Gratz Family Papers. Three of the documents are newspapers: the Federal Union(Milledgeville, GA) dated June 20, 1833 (Moses Sheftall Series); the Daily Morning News(Savannah, GA) dated August 28, 1857 (Sheftall Family Papers), and the Central City(Albany, GA) dated June 12, 1873 (Sheftall Family Papers). The missing newspaper is the Savannah Daily Republican of October 16, 1858. Also included is a Bill of Indenture for Property in Chatham County, GA, from the Moses Sheftall portion of the papers; a ship's manifest with crew signatures for the Hetty and an oversized clipping from a newspaper dated April 10, 1867 regarding Reconstruction and the Supreme Court from the Sheftall family papers.
  - P-8 Barnard and Michael Gratz, Richmond, Letter to John Preston, Surveyor of Montgomery (Photocopy only; not microfilmed or digitized. See P-8: Gratz Family Papers), March 20, 1786; WPA_H-0038; Indexed #278 (Box OS2F, Folder 1)
  - Bill of Sale Indenture for Property in Chatham County, GA to Moses Sheftall, 04/09/1807 (Box OS2F, Folder 2)
  - Schooner Hetty Ships' Crew Commissions with Crew Signatures, September 11, 1781; WPA_H-0027; Indexed #217 (Box OS2F, Folder 3)
  - Provision Return Account Delivery Book for the 1st Regiment Signed by John Vanderhorst for March from St. Mary's to Sunbury with Poem, "Youth has its fling and every fancy but where is charming darling Nancy", 07/14/1778-07/21/1778; WPA_F-0245; Indexed #134; #151 (Box OS2F, Folder 4)
  - Sunbury Prisoners of War on Parole Ration Book, Ledger #11, undated, 09/10/1778 (Box OS2F, Folder 5)
  - Newsclipping of Public Letter from Governor Charles J. Jenkins to the People of Georgia Outlining Appeal to Congress Regarding Reconstruction; Asks Patience with Decision Reached by Supreme Court, possibly Georgia v. Stanton. Unknown Paper., April 10, 1867 (Box OS2F, Folder 6)
  - Federal Union, Milledgeville, Georgia, June 20, 1833; Indexed #308 (Box OS2F, Folder 7)
  - Daily Morning News, Savannah, Georgia, August 28, 1857; WPA_F-0468-B; Indexed #314 (Box OS2F, Folder 8)
  - Savannah Daily Republican[MISSING], October 16, 1858; WPA_F-0468-C; Indexed #315 (Box OS2F, Folder 9)
  - Central City, Albany, Georgia, June 12, 1873; WPA_F-0468-D; Indexed #319 (Box OS2F, Folder 10)